Finding Aid for Hartford Memorial Baptist Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1922-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hartford Memorial Baptist Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1922-2011
Hartford Memorial Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.)
18 linear feet
Detroit, Michigan, African American church. Files concern church governance and policies; church committees and other organizations; and church events, celebrations, and services; also include publications and topical files with information on pastors Charles Hill and Charles Adams.
9930 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were first placed on deposit in December 1998 by Hartford Memorial Baptist Church (donor number 8602 ). The records came through Charles J. Estus, church historian. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open for research.
Between 1910 and 1920 the African-American population of Detroit increased from 5,741 to 40,838. Key institutions in the spiritual and social life of African Americans, African-American churches in Detroit grew in number from six in 1916 to over forty in 1926. African Americans settled on the east side of Detroit first and then migrated west, where there were no African-American churches. Rev. Edward Wendall Edwards approached the pastors of the Second Baptist Church and the Detroit Baptist Union and they both supported the establishment of a new church for the west side of Detroit. In 1917, the First Institutional Baptist Church of Detroit was organized with Rev. Edwards as its first pastor; it was the first African-American religious institution west of Woodward Avenue in Detroit.
Resigning in 1920 to do missionary work, Edwards was succeeded by Rev. Charles Andrew Hill of Detroit. Soon afterwards, the name of the church was changed to Hartford Avenue Baptist Church. One of the earliest buildings in which the church worshipped was at 6326 Hartford; in 1924 a more permanent structure was built on the corner of Hartford and Milford. By 1945, church membership was over 1,000.
Hill believed his mandate included community development and political participation. Under Hill, the church heard the politically persecuted Paul Robeson sing and heard lectures from W.E.B. Dubois in the 1950s when they were both considered subversive individuals. Hill led housing demonstrations and opened the church to union organizers from the Ford Rouge plant.
When Hill retired in 1968, Charles Gilchrist Adams was appointed pastor. Adams grew up in Hill's church and was also a very public leader. Adams had attended the University of Michigan and Harvard Divinity School and, before returning to Hartford as pastor, Adams served as pastor of the Concord Baptist Church in Boston from 1962 to 1969. Under Adams, the congregation soon doubled. In 1974, the church decided to relocate to the former Covenant Baptist Church at 18700 James Couzens Drive. The move was completed in 1977 and membership soon tripled; by 1998 the church had over 7,000 members. The name of the church was changed from Hartford Avenue Baptist Church to Hartford Memorial Baptist Church in 1981.
Adams was president of the Detroit branch of the NAACP and participated in the boycott against Dearborn merchants for not allowing nonresidents in its parks. Adams also believed in using economic power to control the environment in which the church was located and the church bought up properties around it to rent or lease to businesses in the hopes of bringing jobs to the community. Under Adams' guidance, over a dozen programs were developed to work with the community, including a free legal and medical clinic, a tutorial program, a Head Start program, a job placement agency, a crisis support line, a food co-op and a scholarship fund. An exceptionally charismatic leader, Adams was elected for a four-year term as president of the Progressive National Baptists in 1998.
The records of Hartford Baptist Memorial Church are arranged in seven series: Church Governance and Policies, Committees and Other Church Organizations, Events and Celebrations, Services, Topical Files, Publications and Miscellaneous. Covering the years 1922 to the present, the records document the ongoing work of the church. The bulk of the records date from the 1970s, with sparse documentation for the years 1930 to 1959.
Subjects:
Hartford Memorial Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.); African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Hill, Charles A. (Charles Andrew), 1893-1970.; Adams, Charles G. (Charles Gilchrist), 1936-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Church Governance and Policies
  Within the first series, Church Governance and Policies, the annual reports from 1977 to 1980 provide a detailed description of the church's activities and concerns after its move to the new facility. The reports reflect something of the personality of Charles Adams as well. The Leadership Council minutes provide insight into issues of importance to church members, such as the changing economic and social makeup of the neighborhood around the church, the importance of community involvement, and how to involve youth in the church. The folder of information for new members contains histories of the church and other information on the organization and beliefs of the church.
  - Annual Reports 1959, 1977-1980, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and bylaws 1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Deacon Board Manual 1986 (Box 1)
  - Diaconate annual report 1999 (Box 1)
  - Financial
    - Ledger 1922-1929, 2 folders; original and photocopy (Box 1)
    - Ledger 1929-1936 (Box 1)
    - Mortgages 1923-1940 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Reports and Miscellaneous 1922-1929 (Box 1)
    - Hartford Economic Development Corporation Financial Statements 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Council Minutes
    - 1968-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1995 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Membership Directory 1976 (Box 1)
  - Membership Register and Church Records 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Name Change 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - New Member Information undated (Box 1)
  - Officers (Officiary) 1976-1999 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Personnel Policy manual 1985 (Box 1)
  - Policies and Guidelines 1970-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Guidelines for Church Leaders 1976, 1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Other Policies 1986-1987, undated (Box 1)
  - Trustee Minutes 1966-1972 (Box 1)
- Committees and Other Church Organizations
  The series Committees and Other Church Organizations documents committees and groups such as the Women's Day Committee and Hartford Men United, as well as on social service organizations, such as Agape House. Information about the music ministry of the church is also included here along with programs of performances.
  - Birthmonth Clubs 1970-1996 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Building Administration Committee, (includes floor plans) 1991, 1994, undated (Box 1)
  - Children's Church 1999 (Box 1)
  - Endowment Fund Committee 1991 (Box 1)
  - Food Services Committee 1991 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Agape House 1989-1999 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Hartford Institute of Biblical Studies 1988-1993 (Box 1)
  - Hartford Men United
    - General 1978-1996 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Mentoring Program 1996 (Box 2)
  - Hartford Women United/Women's Day Committee
    - Minutes 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - Other 1978-1996 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Head Start 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - Histories of Church Organizations 1945-1995 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Kentake and KAFO Academies undated (Box 2)
  - Music
    - General 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Concert Programs 1979-1995 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
      (include Jubilee Chorus)
    - Senior Choir; Inspirational Chorus 1952-1963 (Box 2)
- Events and Celebrations
  The Events and Celebrations series includes celebratory programs honoring African American history, anniversary celebrations of the installation of Pastor Hill, and various other dinners and pageants.
  - American African Events 1980-1994 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Anniversary Celebrations 1963-2002 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    (include Videotape (VHS): 75th anniversary celebration of Hartford)
  - Calendar of Activities 1985, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Christian Debutante Pageant 1980 (Box 2)
  - Cornerstone Laying April 1, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Drama Group Presentations 1985, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Economic Awareness and Empowerment Day 1984 (Box 2)
  - Harambee Fellowship Dinner 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Memorial Birthday Celebration 1985 (Box 2)
  - Religious Freedom Celebration 1993 (Box 2)
  - Welcome Dinners 1991 (Box 2)
  - Other Events (Box 2)
- Services
  The series Services contains programs for services and revivals dating primarily from the 1990s. The weekly church bulletin and memorial service programs are included within the Publications series.
  - Lenten and Easter Services 1977-1998 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Revivals 1990, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Saturday Services 1996 (Box 2)
  - Special Services 1980-1998 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains information on Charles Hill's nomination as a candidate for the Detroit city council election in 1945, biographical information on Charles Adams, and information surrounding the controversial decision to allow Kmart to build on land owned by the church.
  - Adams, Charles G.
    - Biographical Material and Other 1985-1998 (Box 2)
    - Speeches and Writings 1965-1985 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
      (includes log of church sermons)
    - Programs from services where Adams was the speaker (Box 2)
    - 50th Year Ministry Celebration 2004 (Box 2)
  - Hill, Charles A. (Biographical Material, 1945) (Box 3)
  - Histories 1977, undated (Box 3)
  - Kmart
    - General 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Detroit Planning Commission Meeting on Re-Zoning Area for Super K-Mart 1997 (Box 3)
  - Memorials 1952 (Box 3)
  - Pioneers of Church (Box 3)
- Publications
  The series of Publications is the largest in the collection. In addition to Souvenir Bulletins that contain historical information and photographs of people and facilities, the series also includes an extensive run of the weekly bulletin (currently called the Booster), copies of the articles written by Charles Adams for the Michigan Chronicle entitled "In Our Opinion," and printed obsequies of church members. This series also includes files from the mid-1990s of various church services and programs. Similar earlier materials were placed within the Events and Celebrations series and the Services series.
  - Various
    - Birthday and Wedding Anniversary Calendar (Box 3)
    - Griot, April 1993, February 1997, May 1997 (Box 3)
    - Hartford Business Association Directories 1985-2001 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Souvenir Bulletins 1962-1998 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
  - Booster /weekly church bulletin
    (scattered issues before 1970 mainly anniversary and souvenir bulletins)
    - 1929-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 4)
    - 1978 1982-1986 (Box 5)
    - 1987-1991 (Box 6)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    - 1995-1997 (Box 8)
    - 1998-March 2000 (Box 9)
    - April 2000-2002 (Box 15)
    - 2003-2006 (Box 16)
    - 2007-2008 (Box 18)
    - 2010-2011 (Box 18)
  - "In Our Opinion" column of Charles Adams
    - 1970-1991 (scattered) (Box 10)
  - Obsequies
    - 1960-1993 (Box 11)
    - 1994-2005 (Box 12)
    - 2006-2008 (Box 13)
  - Other programs
    - 1996 1999-2008, 10 folders (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes information regarding church membership, including lists of new members, deaths and funerals files, and church membership transfer files. In addition, there are files relating to the Progressive National Baptist Church and the Michigan Progressive Baptist Church.
  - New members 1959-1967, 1978-1979, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Deaths and funerals 1981-1997, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Letters of transfer 1988-1994 (Box 14)
  - Forms and mimeographed mailings 1985, 1 volumes; 11 folders (Box 14)
  - Athletic Ministrry 1999-2001 (Box 14)
  - Autoporium Developments Plans 1991 (Box 14)
  - Cotillion Club 1973 (Box 14)
  - Hartford Economic Development Corporation proposal 1984, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Hill family papers 2000 (Box 14)
    (photographs of opening dedication program at the Bentley Library)
  - Hill family. Funeral and obituary of Bermecia Morrow-McCoy 2002 (Box 14)
    (includes sound cassettes)
  - Progressive National Baptist (and Michigan Progressive Baptist) publications (Box 17)
    (also includes 1 VHS videotape of convention, 1991)
  - Quilting Sisters Ministry (Box 17)
  - Record of pledges 1965, 1976, undated (Box 17)
  - Roster and Telephone Book, ca. 1973 (Box 17)
  - Senior Citizen Retirement/Shopping Center Village 1991 (Box 17)
  - Planners for church events and other scheduling materials, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 17)